# Elena Gutiérrez Viedma

Website



Age25 (November 10, 1993)Place of birthMadrid, SpainNationalitySpanishEmailelena.gutierrez@imdea.org

http://software.imdea.org/~elena.gutierrez/

**Address** IMDEA Software Institute

Office 342

Campus de Montegancedo s/n 28223 - Pozuelo de Alarcón

Madrid, Spain

#### **About Me**

I am a fourth-year Ph.D. student at the IMDEA Software Institute in Madrid, under the supervision of Prof. Pierre Ganty. Before, I studied a Bachelor's Degree in Mathematics and Computer Science at Universidad Autónoma de Madrid. During my summer breaks from 2013 to 2015, I worked at IMDEA Software with Ganty on formal verification of programs using Horn clauses.

Now, my research interests are mainly focused in the theory of formal languages and automata and its applications to software verification. I am also interested in Horn clause verification, and logic and functional programming.

## **Research Experience**

Sept. 2016 - present IMDEA Software Institute

PhD. in Software, Systems and Computing supervised by Prof. Pierre Ganty

Universidad Politécnica de Madrid

Sept. 2015 - Feb. 2016 IMDEA Software Institute

Bachelor's Project supervised by Prof. Pierre Ganty

**2013 - 2015** IMDEA Software Institute

Three-month research summer internships

#### Education

2011-2016 Bachelor's Degree in Mathematics and Computer Science (360 ECTS)

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid | Average Grade (out of 10) - 8.2

### **Publications**

2019 A Congruence-based Perspective on Automata Minimization Algorithms

P. Ganty, E. Gutiérrez and P. Valero. MFCS 2019

**2018** The Parikh Property for Weighted Context-Free Grammars

P. Ganty and E. Gutiérrez. FSTTCS 2018

**2017** Parikh Image of Pushdown Automata

P. Ganty and E. Gutiérrez. FCT 2017

# **Bachelor's Project**

2016 Linearisation of Index Bounded Sets of Horn Clauses.

Supervised by Prof. Pierre Ganty

This thesis presents a Prolog algorithm that transforms non-linear logic programs into linear

preserving their meaning Grade (out of 10) - 10

#### Schools/Seminars Attended

- Microsoft Research PhD. Summer School. 4–8, July, 2016. Cambridge, UK.
- 2<sup>nd</sup> School on Formal Verification by The Hebrew University. 17–21, December, 2017. Jerusalem, Israel.
- womENcourage 2018, ACM Celebration of Women in Computing. 3–5, October, 2018. Belgrade, Serbia.

#### **Conference/Public Talks**

| March, 2017 | Parikh Image of Pushdown Automata   |
|-------------|---|
|             | S3, Seminar Series at Imdea Software Institute. March 7 <sup>th</sup> , 2017  |
| Sept., 2017 | Parikh Image of Pushdown Automata Presentation at FCT 2017 in Bordeaux, France. September 11 <sup>th</sup> , 2017   |
| April, 2018 | Weighted Context-Free Grammars: Does Parikh's Theorem still hold?<br>S3, Seminar Series at Imdea Software Institute. April 3 <sup>rd</sup> , 2018                             |
| Sept., 2018 | <i>The Parikh Property for Weighted Context-Free Grammars</i> Formal Methods and Verification Seminar at the Université Libre de Bruxelles. September 26 <sup>th</sup> , 2018 |
| Dec., 2018  | The Parikh Property for Weighted Context-Free Grammars Presentation at FSTTCS 2018 in Ahmedabad, India. December 12 <sup>th</sup> , 2018                                      |
| Feb., 2019  | ¿Cómo garantizar que un programa hace lo que esperas?"<br>I+D+M². Mujeres en Montegancedo. February 11 <sup>th</sup> , 2019   |
| March, 2019 | <i>Undecidability and Context-Free Languages</i><br>S3, Seminar Series at Imdea Software Institute. March 25 <sup>th</sup> , 2019   |
|             |   |

### Languages

**Spanish** Native

**English** Fluent TOEFL iBT (Feb. 2016). Total (out of 120): 104

French Basic

## **Programing Languages**

• Prolog, Haskell, C, Python, MFX

#### **Grants**

2017-2021 Predoctoral Contract for PhD. Training Grant (FPI)

Provided by the Spanish Ministry of Economy, Industry and Competitiveness

### **Additional Information**

**Teaching Experience** Support classes for students at secondary education

Mathematics, English, Physics and Chemistry

**Volunteer work** International exchange organization AFS

 $Coordination\ of\ exchange\ activities\ for\ foreign\ students\ in\ Spain$ 

Soñar Despierto Foundation

 $Support\ classes\ for\ students\ coming\ from\ marginalized\ backgrounds$